howdy this is Jim rut and this is the
Jim rut show listeners have asked us to
provide pointers some of the resources
we talked about on the show we now have
links to books and articles referenced
in recent podcasts that are available on
our website
we also offer full transcripts go to Jim
ruts show com that's Jim ruts show com
today's guest is daniel mezack hey Jim
thanks for having me on the show yeah
it's great to have you on the show a lot
of really interesting things to talk
about from your work Daniel's been
coaching executives and teams since 2006
he is a scrum at scale trainer an expert
on business agility and then the author
of three books on organizational change
will talk about the books as we go along
and as usual links to those books will
be available at the episode page at Jim
rut show.com
I want to tell just a little bit how you
got interested in this area and what you
did before yeah so in 1993 I formed a IT
services firm you know consulting firm
and I had operations in three states for
about ten years
you know Rhode Island Massachusetts and
in Connecticut and then with the dot bum
crash in the UK thing all of that
materially changed and I found myself
kind of pretty much on the beach around
2003 not wanting to go back to the
previous thing which was no longer the
happy hunting ground that it once was
and not knowing where I was what was
gonna happen next you know so for about
three years
um I didn't know what I was doing and
then around 2005 2006 I started hearing
this noise about about agility and scrum
you know and XP and started researching
that in 2005-2006 I went to a class
about scrum and in that pretty much put
me on the path I'm on today yes since
then I've been involved in coaching and
training in that area the I first got
exposed to the agile field in 2001 when
I got
to become chairman of a high-end chip
design software company in Ottawa and it
was a amazing little company for recent
college grads who had about two years of
experience at northern telecom had some
very clever ideas and we're on their way
but they needed some organizational help
a little bit of help on fundraising but
one of the things they did have in which
they believed in in a religious fashion
was the use of scrum hmm and so I said
okay I'm just gonna watch here right and
maybe I can give wise man advice when I
see what a ridiculous thing this might
be right has been person who generally
scoffed at management systems
quote-unquote the truth of the manner
the old guy this time just sat there and
didn't say anything just learned and
actually worked great and we did a
second company with some of the same
cast of characters after we sold the
first very successfully and they did it
again then they used a slight variation
on scrum which they essentially had
learned from the first time around and
what's the other one Kanban or some damn
thing it's kind of like a hybrid between
those two yes
and again watched him do it I didn't
have a word to say they clearly knew
what they were doing so I've been
basically participating as involved with
the use of since 2001 and then in 2013 a
little teeny micro startup that I
oversaw for about six months we also
used the variant on it so I was very
impressed or the scope of a team of ten
or less engineers I was convinced that's
what it's for yep and I know but your
ideas are that the concept and
philosophy could be used at greater
scale is that fair to say if you have
certain certain conditions in place yet
you can scale it alright let's jump in
here and talk about the first book I
read in prep for this podcast as my
listeners know I typically spend about
ten hours getting prepped for each
podcast and the first book is called
open space agility Handbook of which Dan
is one of the co-authors but kind of
reading between the lines I'd say it
smelled like you were the main author is
that fair enough
that's fair I pretty much composed the
list of authors you know they were
invited in to help with the book they
substantially helped in
I put them all on the cover that's a
good thing yeah that's a good thing and
essentially the basic framing is around
I would describe it as agile open space
technology could you just unpack that
just a little bit yeah our natural way
of working is to do what we're happy
doing and do what we're passionate about
doing do stuff we have energy around so
open space technology is you could think
of it as a meeting format or an event
design that allows that kind of you know
self-organized behavior to just show up
in surface itself very very quickly the
normal rules of engagement are suspended
everyone's responsible for themselves in
an open space meeting for their learning
for what they contribute for where they
go on what they do so if you have a
great time in open space you can blame
yourself for that and if you have a
terrible time you can also blame
yourself
so you know the natural self-organized
world you know reveals itself in open
space when people are in it and if
you've ever seen a picture of it you
know
sometimes is up to you know seven
hundred eight hundred people sitting in
a circle and the beginning and end of
the meeting it's quite an epic you know
visual and then throughout the day folks
are left to organize their thinking
attention and learning in a way that's
meaningful to them throughout the day
with the others and we use that for
organization level transformation now
how do you staple that to the concept of
agile they seem to be again in my mind
and in my experience limited that it is
I think of agile as a technology
appropriate for a team of not more than
ten maybe on a really good day twelve
engineers how does the concept of agile
for a small team get stapled to this
open space concept which sounds like it
could be up to hundreds of people yeah
so I have a hypothesis about the agile
stuff first a decent definition of agile
is the ability to rapidly identify and
respond to change and to take advantage
of our opportunities and that are
presented by that change the whole idea
of this revolves around self-managed
teams
self-manage meaning they're managing
decisions that pertain to the whole
group so the self-management idea is
core to agility and I have a hypothesis
about this which is most if not all of
the improvement that you're getting from
agility comes from this self-management
behavior right so executive leaders
create the conditions where this can
happen they get out of the way and allow
people to do their thing and when folks
start making decisions you know they
engage and the engagement is associated
with just about every good thing and
then you see this great productivity
improvement improvement and quality
predictability reliability and so on so
on open space technology the meeting
format without a lecture it demonstrates
what this self-managed self-organized
way of working actually looks like so
Harrison Owen composed open space in the
80s the mid 80s and his work predated
the agile manifesto by some 16 years so
you know open space technology the
meeting format you know formulated by
Harrison Owen or what he would say
discovered by him is actually 100%
aligned with agile ways of working in
fact it totally embodies that so when
you go into an organization you bring
open space to an organization the the
executives the workers the managers the
directors everybody they have a big Wow
experience and what they're really
experiencing is the power of
self-management so without a lecture
we're demonstrating how good it can
actually be how efficient it can be and
we bring that in you know an agile way
of working we use that as a sort of
frame for discussing how this thing
really works so is it fair to say that
the con time again trying to get the
concept clear here is that we have agile
as a set of philosophies and tools aimed
at doing work at the team scale and then
when you take those philosophies at
least if not all the techniques and
marry them to the open space meeting
format you are then able to bring at
least some or all of
agile philosophy into larger scale
entities is that reasonable yeah yeah
let me tell you a story right so most
organizations what they do is they do an
agile type pilot so I might bring in
scrum and work with you know three or
four teams and and get them moving and
those are teams that want to actually
work in that way when organizations do
pilots with scrum gym they typically
will look for willing teams to reduce
the risk of failure right so willing
teams committed authority figures the
scrum framework you know that's a
winning combination so most of these
pilots will go pretty good what happens
is they get some really nice
improvements and things they're
measuring and then they immediately want
to scale it to a whole enterprise
there's some problems with that the
primary problem is the leaders get
organizationally amnesia they forget
that the teams that were in those
successful pilots were willing teams so
we go from sort of an opt-in approach to
a mandated rolled out approach and you
know a lot of times that just doesn't
work and and the reason why is because
good agile runs on engaged people and
engage people or people that are
choosing you know in deciding choosing
turns out to be very engaging so there's
this there's this whole relationship
between choosing something and being
engaged and this is exactly the concept
in open space and open space the meeting
is optional to attend no one can make
you you don't have to go to the meeting
that is a requirement of open space so
what we're doing with open space and
organizations Jim is we're trying to
gently introduce the idea of you know
agile organizational change across the
whole organization and we're engaging
that organizations willingness to
proceed you put all the people that are
involved that are affected in a large
all-hands open space meeting that's
invitational you're gonna find out right
away about the organizational readiness
and in willingness to to move forward a
lot of these organizations
they quote roll out you know scrum agile
across their whole organization they
might as well just put the money in the
big pile and fluff it up and sprinkle a
little gas on it and flick a match on
that million dollars you know that would
hurt a lot less people there's also this
kind of infliction of organizational
change today so open space rolls that
back and says let's find out what people
are willing to do and let's invite them
into it and that's how that's how we do
it with open space agility yeah I think
that's very smart because again the you
know the times I've seen it a jewel work
is when the people who are doing it are
committed it's actually from my days as
a corporate technologist you know may or
may not know this back in the day I was
responsible directly and indirectly for
5,000 technologists that today is
Thompson Reuters whoo and that was the
day somewhat of the waterfall method
though at least in my tech groups which
added up to about a thousand people we
didn't use anything quite so rigid as
that but on the other hand we didn't use
anything quite as disciplined as scrum
and I would say that trying to have
forced scrum at scale across 5,000
people strikes me as a daunting task at
the minimum Jim this is this is
happening routinely around the world
today as we're speaking there are
probably three four or five thousand
implementations of exactly what you just
described and the the reason is
basically that you know executives they
want an ABC story of how the change is
going to go meanwhile scrum is an
empirical approach to process control
right so in software being a high
complexity type of an endeavor scrum is
perfect for that the reality is that
we're going to do a little we're gonna
learn a little we're going to inspect
that and we're gonna go again and you
know that just doesn't land with a lot
of authority figures who they want to
hear an ABC plan with an ABC budget so
they really want it they want a
waterfall approach to the implementation
of an empirical approach
and that gets sold all over the world
every single day yeah sounds like a
show ready to happen it's in progress
Jim it's totally in progress even better
I might be able to make a Saturday Night
Live it's not quite fine so now oh I
think I'm getting a better sense of you
know the whole open space agility
concept here so I'm gonna try to restate
it again I tend to do this till I
understand something very clearly which
is your argument is that your open space
meeting technology and things we'll talk
about later like your hundred days etc
yeah yeah are a way to to get an
organization to appropriately adopt
agile techniques at appropriate scale
that's right so one would not expect to
run a 3,000 person division from top to
bottom using scrum that just wouldn't
work but that the teams within that
3,000 person division from whom scrum or
one of the other agile techniques was
appropriate would seduce themselves into
doing so when it was appropriate
something like that well yeah like
organizations have different functions
and in different divisions and
departments so when we talk about
products all of products can run on
scrub at scale certain conditions have
to be in place but it's it's certainly
doable and you can you can create a
delivery machine and point it at
anything
using scrum for product the organization
itself also you know has different
functional areas like HR people ops
legal and compliance and so forth and
you know that they're not going to adopt
perfectly to a you know a scrum approach
but the reality is on the product side
scrum is it is a very good way to
organize your engineering teams you know
at scale so I'm working right now with
an organization that has nine hundred
engineers globally and we're in the
early steps of implementing scrum at
scale and the first thing that I'm doing
with this leadership team with my my
colleagues is we're taking them through
series of one-hour meetings it's a 13 14
person leadership team and I'm
confronting them with the reality of the
scrum guide you know the scrum guide
says things that are
their abrupt in and in harsh the the
primary thing that scrum does is it it
has a set of rules about around decision
rights around the three roll so for
example for the product owner it says
for the product owner to be successful
everyone in the organization must
respect his or her decisions so you know
we're walking through those kinds of
statements in the scrum guide and I'm
asking the leadership team you know what
do you think the level of agreement of
the organization over all right now is
with this with the state you know you're
doing scrum how well are you doing it
and rate it on one to ten where ten is
great and one is really bad and then
rate yourself what what's your level of
willingness to support the statement as
a leader to create the conditions where
this statement can be true and you know
around the world organizations overall
do not go through this exercise they
just roll out scrum to unwilling teams
they know what else the teams what they
think or anything they just roll it out
and a lot of times the CEO wants it or
the CTO wants it you know but you know
you were an executive for decades so you
know that just because you want
something doesn't mean that your team
wants it your leadership team right yeah
let me I have to tell you this story
when I first became a CEO of a
publicly-traded company I brought on one
of my favorite strategy consultants and
he was cynical to the bone and would
just tell you the way it was and the
first day the first five minutes I was
sitting on the imperial throne he said
Jim you know all these buttons and
levers conceptually that are on your
desk
yeah ninety percent of them aren't
attached to anything you could pull the
levers and you can press the buttons but
not a goddamn thing will happen exactly
you know what he was right and of course
you know that was a company where I
didn't build it I built a goddamn it all
those buttons would work but this is one
of our I came in it was essentially a
turnaround and he was absolutely right
most the was broken and so the job
was the unfuck it basically over a
period of time exactly exactly so you
know if you're gonna do good agile you
know you have to create the conditions
or the the space for people to do that
kind of great work
that space is created by authority
figures they create the conditions they
define the game so I work with the
leadership teams around you know
creating those conditions in I want a
very very strong unambiguous yes to the
things that's that the scrum guide lays
out around decision right so they
understand the way decisions are made it
gonna change you know sometimes I kind
of talk to fill them you know like
they'll give me objections to the scrum
decision right so I don't like that rule
about the product owner or whatever I
don't say well hey let me ask you a
question you make decisions today about
product a certain way don't you they're
like well yeah I'm like well how's that
working for you and then we have that
conversation so they're admitting that
the way they make decisions around
product isn't working it's slowing
things down and increase its decision
latency and we're gonna we're going to
use scrum to reduce that decision
latency that's gonna require discipline
and I really love the way you mentioned
that around about scrum you mentioned
scrum requires discipline and I just so
enjoyed these said that earlier because
that's what it takes yeah I just
realized we jumped in to the deep end of
the pool could you take a couple of
minutes and describes how scrum works
let's just use scrum because I think
that's pretty close to a core standard
flavor of agile yeah just give you know
the roles and and and you know this or
the basic how a eight-man team might use
it sure yeah so scrum is a prefabricated
plan for executing on work in three
roles there's a product owner there's a
team and there's a scrum master the
product owner owns the product vision
and maintains a list of things that need
to be done and prioritizes that lists
the team you know serves the product
owners vision by looking at that list to
that prioritized list in a highly
structured planning meeting the team and
only the team has the right to decide
exactly how much of the topmost
prioritized work they can fit into their
time box at Sprint which is one week to
four weeks long
some product owner presented to the team
the team examines it as it stands they
pull as much of the work as they
possibly can into the sprint they have a
conversation about the release plan and
contingencies you know things might
happen during the sprint and then they
go off and they do the sprint and the
rule is that none of that work can
change it's froze and the team knows
exactly what the scope of their work is
and they know how much time they have
they come out of that meeting knowing
those two things and then each day
they're required to depict their
progress and some kind of visual
artifact that anyone in the organization
can look at so it's put somewhere on
public display or you know somewhere on
a shared Drive or something Jim where
anybody at any time can see the work
remaining yeah but in a small company
like the ones where I've used it we
actually used yellow sticky pads on a
wall there you go so anyone at any time
knows exactly where the team stands and
then each day the team has their own
private daily scrum a stand up meeting
which is a kind of status meeting now
interestingly in the status meeting the
authority that they report to is
themselves so each team member basically
reports on what's going on with their
work today and yesterday and what
obstacles they're facing out of that
meeting comes a list of impediment
things that are holding the team back
and there's a facilitator role called
the scrum master whose job is to
basically help the team be great so as
impediments are surfaced during the
daily scrum and through cut through
conversation throughout the work the
scrum master takes care of removing
those impediments and the scrum master
is duly authorized to do so so if
necessary you know the scrum master has
is authorized to go to you know the
highest executives in the company and
straighten things out so this team can
get their work done yeah and and then
when the sprint ends there's a
demonstration of the work stakeholders
are invited to that demonstration the
product owner is there it's their
meeting the team is there they
demonstrate the functionality in the
goal and scrum that the
scrum done extremely well provides for
the possibility of shipping something at
the end of the Sprint so a potentially
shippable increment or product is
produced by the team which implies a lot
right because there has to be a lot of
testing it has to be production ready
you know all of these kinds of things
have to be in place so most
organizations aren't there but we move
in the direction of improvement every
single sprint and then you know at the
end of a sprint we have a retrospective
meaning we look back on what we've just
experienced and get some learning from
that and form some new experiments that
we want to try in the next sprint to
improve a little more and then we repeat
the cycle and and that's that's how
scrum works and the team size is the
team size is never less than three
people are more than nine or ten but in
that range yeah very interesting I think
you did a good job laying that Adam a
few comments I wanted to make just don't
think I'll start at the bottom and work
my way up sure which is you talk about
the in theory you need to be able to
ship something at the end of each sprint
you know I to Matt down a little bit and
I say you have to have a deliverable
that actually runs at the end of each
spread you know a deliverable meaning
and internal deliverable that actually
runs which then implies that you have a
you have to have a discipline of
incremental builds all the time right
none of it none of those build it and
then or then right right right then test
and then hope it all passes a test wrong
so you have to compile every night at
the worst and in this day and age you
might as well do it continuously and
which means that you have to invest and
this is something that if you don't do
this you probably shouldn't do scrum in
a big corporate environment which is
that you need to invest in something
that's called DevOps which is a new
career and if you're a person looking
for a job that will pay well for quite a
long while DevOps is one which is what
is the operational infrastructure
necessary to be able to do continuous
builds and continuous deployments
without having to be touched by human
ants and there's all these really neat
tools these days that do just that and
then the final part I would put my
flavour on it you're gonna have
deliverables at the end of each sprint
you
incremental builds and DevOps it makes a
lot of sense to do what's called test
oriented development which is you
literally write the tests first for
every little tiny bit of code down at
the that's right now at the function
level so that when you when you push the
code to the server and the DevOps magic
occurs and it's all built all those
tests are run and if they don't pass you
get a yellow flag back to you by email
or slack or something within a minute or
two of the time you checked your code in
and you might check in at two o'clock in
the afternoon at 2:05 you get a message
on slacks as oops your code failed the
following three tests and that means
that you ready you got to work on it so
that certainly by the end of the Sprint
and probably better that by the end of
the day you fixed those problem I love
that I'm glad you're bringing up DevOps
you know like when a Cub programmer goes
to work for Facebook or Amazon the first
thing that they do with them is they
have them push some code to production
the very first day so you can think of
DevOps is a kind of radicalized agile
right so what happens is all of the
repetitive tasks that no developers want
to do anyway it's being relegated to
robots you know programs and computers
and what's what's happening there is the
authority to make decisions is is being
democratized Jim previously like in
these big firms like insurance companies
brokerage firms banks government
agencies they have their Quality
Assurance department which is an entire
you know an entire thing with a with a
head and a budget and hire fire
authority and all the stuff in the new
world the devil ops radicalized agile
the cub programmer now is authorized to
push things to production there are no
gatekeepers if it passes through those
tests like you say there is a 99.99999
99% chance that all the code is good so
what's happening is a total revolution
Wow I wouldn't go I wouldn't go that far
you know truthfully code coverage is
never that good not a 9.99 it's probably
98 or 99 so you can still have
which is why if you're gonna push it up
to production you have to have a way to
revert real fast and that's again part
of Deb
ray-ray right so Amazon your Facebook
they pushed off the production four
hundred five hundred times a day I may
probably pull it back go ahead you were
three times right right so what this is
doing Jim is it's upsetting everybody
everyone's upset why because people who
made decisions yesterday do not make
them today the QA people used to make
decisions yesterday now the cub
developers make those decisions that's
upsetting to people so there's this
whole revolution in decision rights
that's going on that's being driven by
this agility stuff in develops is a
radicalized form of that I'm so glad you
brought it up because it's so show so
what's happening that you know the
revolution in decision rights in
software development it's just amazing
we have I was doing a readiness
assessment for something like your open
space agility one of the things I
absolutely make sure if I said the word
DevOps and a senior executive looked at
me cross-eyed I'd say maybe I better
come back next year because DevOps would
seem to be central to make this kind of
stuff work particularly at scale oh yeah
but you understand no I mean any
organization can spend 100 maybe 150 200
thousand bucks and set this up okay but
the resistance is in the entrenched
bureaucracy of QA and some of these
other departments that don't want to
evolve they like things the way they are
and don't want to lose their head count
right yeah they have their jobs they
don't want to lose their jobs goddamnit
you don't want to break the iron rice
bowl exactly that's what's happened
them
your horses they wrote in on write their
horses right and then you barbecue the
horse good alright that's absolutely
good you know just critical stuff I'm
gonna pop up to my favorite hobby horse
and you know people that work with me
know that if I actually had to do a real
job sometime which I sure sure I
hope I never have to do it would be as a
product manager I don't even though I
don't think I ever had that title the
it's what I always was right yeah and
the biggest value I believe I added into
corporate America in say the 1990s was
introducing ruts
eyal product management okay and also
into the startups and you know the key
part was the product manager had to be a
really senior job and frankly should
report to the CEO and if you can imagine
that caused all kinds of storms in
the same way DevOps does woohoo but when
I then learned about agile in 2001 and
they made you know this focus on the
product owner I said oh I love this this
is like a miniature version of Rutt
product management and you highlighted
the part that is absolutely necessary
but usually doesn't happen in which is
the product owner has to be strong
enough to have credibility up and down
the chain yes and if you turn the
product owner into some you know 22 year
old person fresh out of college with a
clipboard that they got a bunch of
function points from the marketing
department you know it's gonna be a
show oh yeah the product owner has to be
able to put themself in the place of the
customer absolutely and they have to
really to really know the business and
they have to have more than a clue about
the technology and they have to have the
respect of of everyone in the
organization and and this is a rare
person that someone who relishes
Authority and has the goods now are you
seeing that out in your practice and the
world that people are willing to or
confined whether they're willing or not
but that really good product owners are
appearing when needed you know my whole
approach to this around the rules is
that in an organization the best thing
to possibly do is describe the role
identify people who might be able to fit
the role get them all in one room and
invite them to come in and occupy the
role and instead of assigning it this
this will this will create the best
possible product manager so you can get
you you you Whittle it down to the you
know the people in your organization
that you think meet the criteria you get
them in one room explain the gravity of
the situation and allow them to opt in
this is the fastest way to get a good
product knowing that I know of I like
that that's great because it's key
without it ain't gonna work didn't work
in fact my mentor the very first
PowerPoint I ever did on rut style
product management
showed the product manager as the Greek
god Janus with you know the face that
faced in future actually I said it has
to look to the technology what's
possible and to the market what's needed
in fact I then eventually it took me
about a year I cooked product management
this was not quite the same as being a
product owner but it's very close yeah
down to one sentence do you want to hear
the rutti in one sentence on product
management sure it is the optimal
trade-off between the doable and the
desirable yeah and that raises a whole
issue of value right exactly someone has
to know what is desirable but that's
what being the target for the customer
is all about yeah in value value has
many dimensions and that's something
that is hotly discussed during product
development you know and that's how you
prioritize things but the end of the day
you got to have one person make the
calls my view Jeff Sutherland refers to
it as the single ringabel neck you know
and now I hope you'll interview him on
your show Jeff Sutherland is the the
co-creator of scrum he's a West Point
grad after that he graduated top in the
top gun fighter pilot program he flew
103 recon missions over North Vietnam in
an f4 over the treetops the mortality
rate was 50% people who had that job he
was in the Air Force for 11 years then
when that stuff and other things and
then after that he went on and got some
got a PhD in statistics from Stanford
and he had he did cancer research as a
professor at the University of Colorado
and he really got into complex adaptive
systems when he started studying biology
hels belles ii no more do you know this
guy hook us up yeah it definitely hook
you up yeah yeah guy who flies phantoms
above treetops I have some personal
history on that and isn't the complexity
hell yes and invented scrum god damn
right we'll have him on the gym Roger
I'm telling you he's got he's got
something to say and he made this rule
about the product owner having
command authority over the
prioritization in the backlog and it's
always one person not a committee and
this is how you just you know reduce
reduce complexity really really fast you
know the developers can go to one person
to get an answer there's no ambiguity
about it there's a lot of decisiveness
that decision latency is really really
low you know the quality of what's being
produced is very high if you have a good
competent product or and yeah Jeff Jeff
composed scrum in the nineteen nineteen
ninety started in 1993 I actually was
teaching at that time I was teaching
Microsoft platforms and tools I was
working at the company called idx in
Boston the later got purchased by GE GE
Healthcare and I was here in these
noises from from some people some of the
developers in my classes about this this
guy Sutherland the new CTO and he's got
this thing scrum and we have this daily
stand-up meeting we have the ends of
these questions and all those kind of
stuff what was actually happening was
the genesis of scrum right under my nose
but I was too busy they'd really even
notice in those days in 1993 Jeff
created a system where when the work is
at the edge of chaos you can bring it
down from Kate you know the edge of
chaos to you know complex and from
complex to complicated and wrap your
hands around it and increase the
predictability and reliability of
software development you know as you
know software development you know
predictions in the beginning are just
wild ass guesses Jim write this like two
standard deviations you know or very
variance in in in in the range of what
could possibly happen right so through
experience we we narrow that cone of
uncertainty you know through getting
direct experience you know that there's
a couple isn't available they're very
interesting the first one is just going
and doing something is superior to
talking about it right that's number one
absolutely get direct experience
inspecting spirits right and then the
second lesson that's really interesting
is the quality of software turns out to
be a function of the quality of the
interactions
in communications buy-in between the
team members so scrum encourages very
very high quality
interactions through the daily scrum the
Sprint planning sprint review you know
this there's a real efficiency of
communication there that that's really
beautiful and it's it can create
something really great yeah absolutely
and we discovered in the 80s something
that was I would say conceptually a
precursor which again back in the early
70s and early 80s people would have the
various sub parts of the team's working
on their modules and they wouldn't bring
them together until ridiculously late in
the process that's always a bad idea at
least in my companies one of my
innovations was the earliest possible
end-to-end system right we could have
fairly minimal functionality but the
goddamn thing had to work from one end
to the other and most of the businesses
I was involved in was building online
information systems that work at a at
least the continental scale sometimes a
worldwide scale there was an awful lot
of involved to make it end-to-end
actually work but I'd get into end to
work you know about three or four weeks
into a year-long project and people said
that's impossible I don't know it's not
we just put wherever we need to
right and we will have information
flowing from end to end and back again
in three or four weeks and then we will
work from there and that's you know
again conceptually similar though not as
fully robustly grown out as you know the
scrub approach and its incremental
builds and the damn thing you know
actually works every day yeah yeah so so
it's it's so great to be talking to a
software guy about a software
development process right this whole
this whole thing with with with that you
know agile scrum organizational scaling
of scrum and so forth points to the fact
that it's the quality of the
interactions the communication that
determines the quality of the product so
actually the more discipline we are in
communicating the better the quality of
the product that's that's that's the
lesson of scrum scrum as it happens to
be and has been tuned to be a pretty
good approach and you do make the point
in your book and I think this is
important to throw out here they even
though you know my experience has all
been scrum one case was a homemade
variant of scrum but there are several
other disciplines of agile out there and
your books are quite clear that you
should not prescribe one or the other
that is I've read them that teams should
choose which one of the agile approaches
that they want to use yeah your
listeners they want to really do some
research on this they can go in in
Google the agile in position or the
agile in position revisit it where
you'll read essays about how processes
or you know so-called agile processes
are being imposed on teams meanwhile
self-management is where all of the all
of the goodness comes from and you're
killing it with the prescription right
you're prescribing something to the team
and not self managing anything at all
because you're not deciding anything so
this whole this whole concept of
deciding Jim is absolutely key to team
productivity so you know leadership
needs to look at this as a game design
so yeah certain decisions are set aside
for formally authorized leaders and
teams don't make those decisions but a
certain number of decisions that do not
fall below a certain threshold in terms
of frequency or number are given to the
team why because the decisions generates
engagement it gets in the head of the
developers and they get in the game and
now they're really creating something if
the decisions they're making falls below
a certain frequency or or number or
volume they will check out they will
literally start to just say you know I
don't care whatever Bob says and and
that's what it's gonna be yeah I hate
that when people just become hands
forget it right but the company has died
right right we have to have heads and
hands all the time and there's also this
concept of learned helplessness have
ever heard of this world oh yes I don't
know how much you've read of my writings
about game B but that is we call a core
example of game a malware is learned
helplessness but I you explain for the
audience would it be well what it base
means is at some point if you're
experiencing pain and you try to get
away from it and you can't get away from
it at some point you give up and even
though the exit door is right under your
nose
you won't even you won't even look for
it anymore and you just resign yourself
to the pain because you know other
people's other people's situation is
good but what mine really sucks you know
and when that happens the productivity
drops dramatically in exponential
fashion so what's happening is there's
if you if you learn it over the teams
you if you take all the decisions away
you make all the decisions for them they
will give up on engaging and then they
will also give up on everything and
they'll just become zombies and this is
what goes on in a lot of organizations
all over the world you know and scrum is
actually a way out of that right because
it's saying in through its rule set no
some of the decisions belong to the team
here's the definition of those decisions
and these these rules are not to be
trifled with if you want to produce good
software and so one of them let's get
back to the topic is that the team
should be allowed to choose which a
jewelled discipline they want to follow
is that correct absolutely because not
every team not every project or not
every program not every product is an
agile product some are some set
sunsetting projects that are you know
well understood and do not require
empiricism for the divino for process
efficiency you know it's a lot of
projects or ABC products or ABC but new
product development a lot of variants in
it a lot of unprinted predictability a
lot of uncertainty you use empirical
process control for that you use
something like scrum that's your way out
of it
but at my point I guess I'm getting a
more narrow point is that the executives
should allow the teams to choose which
of the agile disciplines they might want
to use that's right an open-space
agility what we say is the constraint
that we put in you know we have a 90-day
experimental window where we try some
new process and the constraint is the
agile principles the twelve agile
principles in the manifesto so what we
say to the teams is you
any process you like but don't violate
these principles if you violate these
principles we're gonna take you out
you're gonna get a talking-to but go
ahead use whatever you like within
within these constraints and that turns
out to be rather confining but also
rather liberating at the same time
because they are choosing within a
fairly choosable range right it's a
narrower range but there's still some
choice there they can use Kanban they
can use scrum they can use other
empirical approaches and the act of
choosing is very engaging and that's you
know the team itself becomes happier
that happiness gets associated with you
know up tempo up tone and in boom
outcomes high quality product just for
getting for our audience who many of
them are not professional software
developers but they may be executives
who have those functions under them what
are some of the names of some of the
other approaches other than scrum just
so people have heard the words yeah the
two primary tools that are used today
Jim are the Kanban method which is
pioneered by a fellow named David
Anderson and scrum and then within that
you know there's there's other practices
that are used so for example under the
heading of XP or extreme programming
there's pair programming continuous
integration ideas like this that that
you incorporate and make part of your
your your sort of role your own method
so if you go to extreme programming
you'll see you know many things in there
like refactoring this kind of thing
refactoring is is a programming practice
where you restructure the code it
doesn't change the functionality but it
increases the overall robustness of the
code reduces the brittleness makes it
softer makes it more malleable you know
this kind of thing yeah let's let's now
pop up a level we've talked a lot about
agile itself now let's talk about your
bigger picture open space technology
married to agile wanting to take people
through what open space is and get one
to some detail and you know talk about
your principles and the roles and that
kind of thing take five or ten minutes
all right so open space technology you
know what is it it's basically it
basically creates the conditions where
people can be themselves where they can
make decisions and act on what they want
to learn and how they want to contribute
so let's talk about the starting
conditions for an open space meeting in
an organization right it's basically
three or four starting conditions maybe
five here they are number one we have a
matter of mind-numbing complexity where
no one person has the answer or claims
to right that's number one number two is
there's a diversity of opinion about it
pro and con and people really care about
it so there's heat around the issue pro
and con about how to solve this thing
everyone has an opinion about it the
third condition is this high potential
for conflict as we process this thing
and the fourth one is a decision time of
yesterday like we've already waited too
long and we need to do something now
right so those conditions are ideal for
enterprise wide organizational change
right
this makes the open space meeting you
know highly conducive to an efficient
change experience so the open space
meeting is Invitational in nature no one
can make you go to it a formally
authorized higher up authorizes the time
and the space develops a theme which is
wide enough to contain everyone's you
know issues but narrow narrow enough to
focus the group typically that's that's
developed with a cross-section of the
people of influencers and in people in
the organization and then the the
organization's given a couple weeks to
process you know an invitation that this
leader sends out then when the day comes
the people who are strongly attracted to
the issue who feel passionate and
responsibility around the issue they
show up at the meeting let me let me
jump in let me jump in here just for a
second one thing I try to do in all my
podcast is get down to tangible examples
and so as you're going through this I'd
love to
an example that we both agree would be
appropriate for use of this process and
as I was listening to you it struck me
that one that fit all three of your
criteria in the right context would be
the classic problem for a successful but
still early-stage company is what should
our next product be yes that is a great
theme statement and so interesting that
you put a question mark at the end of it
because themes typically have a question
mark at the end because question marks
tend to open the conversation where a
period tends to close the conversation
write them and frankly one of the things
that some startups I've been involved
with is should we even have a next
product or should we continue to just
invest in our current product and it's a
big tension there's lots of controversy
and it's a big stake yes because it
could be you know half of our free cash
flow next year do we put it into
improving our current product and we
build a next product right so let's use
that as when you're listening to Daniels
talk about the process think in mind
that this is for you know a company that
has one product doing 4 million a year
they've just reached breakeven positive
cash flow and should we have a next
product and if so what will it be
that will be our our high-stakes topic
so continue beautiful yeah so so the the
formally authorized leader who's gonna
function as a sponsor in the host who's
going to be the inviter sends out an
invitation refers to the theme refers to
the opportunities and the threats that
the group is facing invites everyone to
show up kind of sets the boundaries for
the thing namely that you know we're
looking for some solutions is going to
be a book of proceedings that's
generated and we intend to act on those
proceedings after we fin of this meeting
so the meeting is just the beginning
we're going to use the proceedings as a
basis for action moving forward they
send out as widely as they possibly can
as many people that might be affected by
the issue we're invited to the meeting
and then either they go or not they all
receive the proceedings that sent to
them it's like a PDF on a shared network
drive or something like that after the
event happens now inside the invitation
they might provide a link that kind of
describes what open space is an open
space is a as a gathering
it's an invitational gathering around a
theme
and there's five principles to open
space and and here it's in this one law
right so here's the five principles
right first one is wherever it happens
is the right place you know there's no
where ever you do an open space it's the
perfect place it's it's good enough it's
going to happen exactly one time they're
in this way and and we're doing it right
here the second one is whenever it
starts is the right time the idea here
is that the normal rules of punctuality
are suspended in open space the meeting
will start when it starts and that's
pretty much when the people show up when
they all sit down if it's supposed to
start at 9:00 people get there early you
know maybe it starts quote-unquote early
people if people show up a little later
maybe it's quote-unquote late
there is no earlier late in open space
there's just whenever it starts the next
principle is whoever comes are the right
people so when we have one of these
meetings the people who show up we know
for sure why they showed up and that's
to say we're attracted to the invitation
right the people who didn't show up
there's there's eighty-seven thousand
reasons for no but there's only one
reason for a yes and that's that they
found the invitation attractive so
whoever shows up are the right people
people who found an invitation
attractive then the next principle is
whatever happens is the only thing that
could have happened
there's no preset agenda in an open
space meeting there's all kinds of
things that can happen and occur so
there's a slogan and open space be
prepared to be surprised right so one
definition of being surprised is that
you learn something so there's a lot of
learning that goes on in open space the
last principle is when it's over it's
over so some small sessions throughout
the day might end you know a little
early they might they might go out in
the hall and continue the whole day we
don't know how long a session is going
to go or who's going to show up what's
going to be said what's going to emerge
so these principles are recited by the
facilitator during the event
everyone assembles in a big circle the
sponsor who invited everyone reminds
everyone about the opportunities the
threats the theme why we're here and
then introduces the facilitator and then
the facilitator will you know explain
these principles now I've facilitated
dozens of these meetings and what what I
find happens is by the time again around
to the third principle a lot of people
start smiling at me and it's because
they realize that this whole five
principles in one law thing I'm going to
tell you the law in a minute
it's just it's a sort of metaphor for
the fact that you're free so as I recite
the principles I get the feeling okay
I'm free to do what I want nobody can
make me do what I want here
nobody can not not do what I want but
nobody can make me do anything that I'm
unwilling to do at this meeting we're
all basically equal and authority here
so when they get that they start smiling
at you and this is this is the vibe of
open space so one of the things one of
the conditions is a high potential for
conflict there's a law there's one law
and open space here's the lock the law
of two feet if you are not getting the
kind of learning that you are seeking or
I'm getting the opportunity to make the
kind of contribution that you want to be
making your two feet can take you
somewhere else where you can get those
things
leave where leave the session you're at
and go to another one so there is a
couple of sort of sub roles in this open
space thing there's a there's a sponsor
there's a facilitator and then there's a
participants but the participants can
also can function as what we might call
bumblebees
they just move from session to session
they don't spend too much time in any
one session they kind of pollinate the
conversation across all the different
small group sessions that have taken
place and then there's this concept of
you know this behavior like a butterfly
people hang out they don't go to any
sessions and don't call any sessions
they're usually found by the food and
beverages having conversations with
people and they're just in the space
right so the bumble bees and the
butterflies yeah so again let's get down
to tangible so again as I recall how
this thing works there's an opening
meeting where everybody shows up right
yeah big circle yep big circle everyone
so let's say 500 let's say the company
has a hundred people they all show up
and like a master of ceremonies as I
recall starts the thing off so let's
start
you know just run they run the example
through yeah this part's just ends up
welcomes everyone reminds everyone about
the opportunities and threats in the
theme hopes everyone has a great day and
reminds them that we're here to get
those proceedings because we're gonna
act on them afterwards then that that
highly authorized the authority figure
who invited everyone sits down or well
introduces the facilitator and sits down
and then the facilitator stands up and
takes the people through the rest of the
process of getting underway
so you could think of it like this
there's a convergence of everyone at the
beginning of the meeting Jim and then
there's a divergence throughout the day
where we move into small groups like so
for example at one o'clock there might
be seven different small meetings going
on in the big room one in each corner
and you know spread out around the
entire hall usually these meetings are
held in a very large you know Ballroom
in a in a hotel or something like that
so if you're in a small session you can
look around and see six seven of eight
other sessions going on and you can see
your friends colleagues and peers at
those sessions and you can also count
the attendance at those sessions and you
can listen to the noise level of what's
going on and then the level of passion
you know if something grabs you you can
just get up and leave and go see what's
going on over there that's what goes on
throughout the day so at any given time
at one o'clock at two o'clock at three
o'clock there's seven or eight different
things that you can graze on topics and
when the meeting opens people announce
those sessions and they put them on a on
a grid on the wall there's a big blank
wall at the beginning of the beginning
and at the end of the beginning that
wall is filled up with sessions in each
each session is it's going to occur at a
certain time in a certain place
throughout the day and people can go up
to that wall and plan their
day and at any given time at 1 o'clock 2
o'clock or three o'clock this you know
seven things to pick from 8 things to
pick from and then at the end we reek we
reconverge and we have a closing circle
and that's where people offer their
reflections on their experience today we
have a formal closing and then we then
everyone so we D convene and everyone's
dismissed sounds pretty straightforward
now you keep the available sessions up
on a physical board I'm thinking in my
head it'd be kind of cool to have an app
so that you know new new sessions could
come and go and you could look at your
app and especially well if you're gonna
have your right to vote with your feet
you could say god damn this session
sucks let's see what's happening right
now all right yeah have you tried
anything like that you know I have a
great story about that for you if you
want I could tell you about it sure it
was actually a capital one it was the
largest open space I ever did they were
expecting 400 people at the event we did
in two different cities we did it in the
first city I was a I brought some people
in who had more experience than me with
with open space because I felt that I
needed that help and one of the women
who I invited she came up to me and she
was very gentle about it and everything
but she said listen Daniel you know
tomorrow this we were setting up for the
night before and she said listen Daniel
you know tomorrow there's going to be
like you know over 400 people here and
you know the marketplace wall at the
this this big grid is called the
marketplace
it's where the sessions go where the
people post the sessions you know that
marketplace is so big and people don't
won't have much experience with this at
all and you might want to position
ourselves to you know be be to receive
them and kind of teach them you know how
to post to the wall you know I said well
thank you for that it's a good
suggestion let me think about it tonight
you know I'll give you my answer
tomorrow about what we're doing you know
and the next day I woke up and got ready
and I realized no this is all about self
management and self organization
I'm not going to manage anything I'm not
going to authorize the management of
anything here we're gonna we're gonna
see what happens so I went we went to
the space and I I told Linda the one who
made the suggestion you know my my
decision and she's like well okay
and then we opened up the the the
opening and we went through the one law
the five principles to be prepared to be
surprised and everything else about open
space we told them what to do and how to
do it and then invited him to come in
the center of the circle and write their
session down and grab the microphone and
announce it to the group and this one
guy just made a beeline for the center
of the circle and immediately announced
this session put it on the wall and then
he hung out over there and then other
people did the same thing they headed to
the wall and he guided them and coach
them on how to do the marketplace what
that dude had going on was he had an app
on his phone that he wanted everyone to
use which which would socialize the
marketplace and made it easy for people
to keep it in their phone and he wanted
to make sure everyone had a shot at
using his application so that's kind of
cool w guys that is there now a commonly
used app for that purpose there are some
open space apps that automate and
facilitate the marketplace and also the
use of online open space so I've done
open spaces online you know with global
audiences up to 200 people using zoom
video yeah I remember we did one for
rally point alpha it was kind of about
two thirds of shitshow but that wasn't
your fault okay I don't remember that
Jordan show it up after having a certain
procedure yeah I let him in but anyway
that's that's ancient history
they've done a good job of describing
what an open-space meeting is now let's
pop up to your next level of abstraction
at least as I took it out of your book
which is let's say a company has to
convince itself it wants to deploy agile
where appropriate let teams choose to
use agile or not to choose what's flavor
of an agile or not etc and you've
embedded this as a first round of what
you called a hundred days of
experimentation could you talk about the
framework of a hundred days of
experimentation and how open space and
agile essentially self-organized over a
hundred days within an organization yeah
so when you bring procedural change ways
of working change organizational change
that creates anxiety people get worried
and when people are worried and afraid
they can't learn very good and you know
agile is all about learning adapting and
changing and pivoting so what we're
doing there is we're bracketing the
learning experience so it has a
beginning a middle and an end that
begins and ends with an open space
meeting and in the middle we're going to
use that we're going to do
experimentation we're gonna do iteration
we're gonna do adaptation and we're
gonna do inspection right so those are
core agile ideas we're gonna we're going
to inspect we're going to adapt we're
gonna work in iterations and we're going
to experiment in an iterative fashion so
what we're really doing here is we're
taking those team level ideas Jim and
we're making them first-class objects at
the level of enterprise and we're
executing on a hundred day iteration of
change where there's an inspection at
the end we're gonna have a referendum on
what worked what didn't work and what we
want to change at the enterprise level
and this has a profound effect on people
that'll resist it okay because they're
not being asked to do this for the rest
of their lives they're being asked to do
this for a hundred days so what we do is
we create what I call a chapter of
learning and that is is bookended by
these two open space events so at the
first open space and this is key the
leader the sponsor the host says to the
folks not just we're here for the
proceedings but if you like this meeting
you know in a hundred days we're doing
this again
so suspend your disbelief and act as if
and pretend that were what we're about
to embark on in the next 90 days might
actually work okay if it doesn't we're
all gonna get it here everyone's gonna
get a hearing in a hundred days we're
going to inspect this thing and stuff
that didn't work we're gonna drop like a
bad habit but we're moving in the
direction of improvement one way or the
other
that's the
but and that's interesting and I think
it's I would say psychologically wise is
one of things I've taken away from my
business career is that most people
really don't like ambiguity right
there's only a few of us maniacs who
actually thrive on it but they're
willing to tolerate it in tolerable
doses and so what you're doing here is
saying we're dosing this ambiguity for
you that's exactly it that's exactly
right and and that's a very astute
observation
what what what happens when you bring
when you bring the stuff to an
organization is people get real nervous
because here's what's really going on
Jim
we are refactoring the authority
distribution schema when we bring this
agile stuff on people who made decisions
about product yesterday don't make them
today other people don't that makes a
lot of people nervous about their kids
college education about their own
mortgage about their car payment and all
this kind of stuff right their
retirement the whole nine yards so so
it's very triggering because it's
triggering this fight flight and
survival instincts and then when people
are triggered like that they you know
they're not behaving rationally so what
we're doing here is we're reducing the
anxiety that is brought on by this
ambiguity that you're talking about Jim
again I compartmentalized it and further
you I like the the concept where again
there is no dictating to the teams that
they must choose agile but they're gonna
learn about it and here's some ways that
it may be good for them if they want to
they get to choose which is kind of cool
then now popping up one more level as I
understand your process you then have a
repeating of these hundred days after
the first hundred days if things went
well enough people want to do ya know
regarding the hundred days what we know
from experience now is that 45 to 90
days is the sweet spot okay
90 days is like you know one one
material quarter on the calendar 45 days
is half of that and lately there's been
a rash of this trend towards okay ours
because of the John Doerr book and that
maps neatly to 90 day iterations so 45
to 90 days is pretty much the Stan
that we're using now okay but in terms
of in terms of what you're saying yeah
we're going to use iteration to just
like what scrub the the metaphor is in
scrum you have sprint planning you have
the Sprint you have the Sprint review in
open space agility you have the first
open space meeting you have 90 days of
experiment with the new way of working
and then you have the second open space
meeting and that frame allows people to
make meaning of the situation so that
like your startup example where should
we build a new product or not you know
should we continue to go in our first
product should we build the next product
where we going to get the money from all
this kind of stuff coming out of that
first meeting there's a book of
proceedings it's got a bunch of ideas in
it the organization is going to act on
some of those ideas in a you know 45 to
90 day period and the idea is they will
look back and look forward in the next
open space for instance maybe it came
out of the first meeting here you know
here's some research we need to do all
right here's a little prototype we need
to try to build right and we can't build
the prototype and we probably shouldn't
try to build the product right that's
right so there could be it could be some
action item is there any formal
mechanism and open space to cook down
the book to action items or is it not
intended for that yeah open space
meetings are intended to generate
dialogue and ideas the Proceedings that
come out of an open space meeting that
you know our output of it out of an open
space become input into action planning
they're not quite there but the neck
typically the next day so so this is
what typically I've done and works
really really well you have the meeting
the next day the chairs are all in a
circle you still in the same room people
come in and they inspect the proceedings
they spend 30 40 minutes browsing the
proceedings because you know you can't
go to every single session but every
single session is documented in the
proceedings
so you leave through the proceedings you
thumb through it
you pick off the ideas the themes and
the major ideas that are in there you
pick out the seven or eight top once
those are presented to the you know the
leadership group the leadership group
picks four or five things that they want
the whole enterprise to focus on
and then you look for champions who are
gonna gonna pull that together in the
next 90 days they work directly with
executive leadership yeah and they're
authorized to to champion that issue so
what we usually do there in that session
is we put one issue per flipchart on
around the room so if there's five
issues is five flipcharts each one with
a different issue and then executive
leader stands up and explains that we're
looking for people to champion these
things in the next 90 days but before
you jump out of your seat let's explain
the gravity of what this means and then
they lay out the constraints like one of
the constraints might be if you
volunteer you can't unvoluntary
you're in for 90 days okay that's cool
yeah you also commit to you know meeting
with us once a week or every two weeks
and you know some other constraints you
know typically what you'll do is take
the bottom 10% of somebody's workload
and and distribute it to other people so
they have ten percent of their time to
work on this issue and that generates a
tremendous amount of engagement when
that's over and the leader says okay
those of you that want to champion these
issues you know go stand next to the one
that's really hot for you and then
usually about five six percent of the
people get up and they stand up and they
stand up next to those issues and then
we have kind of a science fair kind of
approach after that where everyone else
gets up and grazes around and then
you've got the night the 45 to 90 days
kicked off and you've got champions and
you've got those issues and it's it's a
separate what I'm saying is it's a
separate event and a separate function
there's dialogue then there's deciding
in action and okay then I'll talk about
the next meeting what does that look
like
yeah so you mean like after the
experimental period has passed yes yeah
what that looks like is here's what
happens there okay we talk about people
gaming the meeting right that's actually
a form of self management and self
organization when people learn about
this open space meeting format and they
learn that it's really open what they'll
tend to do is conspire with their
friends
to move the second meeting in the
direction that they want it to go so the
second meaning is up like a
retrospective and a prospective it's a
retrospective on the past 90 days what
worked what didn't work what do we want
to change and it's also a prospective on
what's the next chapter look like and
and what are the next set of experiments
that we want to do so what happens is
the real passionate and responsible
people they will tend to talk to each
other and start to sort of strategize
and plan how they're going to play the
second meeting and that's when it gets
really interesting so I was in one
company where the scrum masters
conspired around getting a product
roadmap out of the second meeting and
the product guy was not the least bit
interested in that and within about a
month and a half that guy was gone he
quit because after the second meeting
what was in the Proceedings was we want
a roadmap that looks at at least 90 days
190 180 days would be better and they
went to him and he's like no I don't
think we're gonna be doing any of that
and then they went to his boss who was
the general manager and we got that
meeting and those as those scrum masters
facilitated a half a day or almost full
day meeting product roadmapping session
where they got that roadmap and kind of
deauthorized this product guy and it
wasn't too long after that that he quit
and then progress that that company
really escalated because he was blocking
so these are the kinds of things that
happen in these in these meetings yeah
very cool well I think that's where
we'll transition away from your first
book to one of your other books I picked
two of them to read the second one is
called inviting leadership and again
there'll be a link to it on our episode
page at Jim Rutte show com
why don't you talk a little bit about
this idea of inviting leadership I
actually found it quite intriguing might
be nice just to introduce it sir yeah
the idea here Jim is that you're in an
era of full employment in an era of
mobility and an era of change your best
work or
are at-will employees they're really
volunteers so if you're not mixing in
some invitations with those delegations
you might be losing some of your best
people because they have a strong drive
for autonomy and the idea here is
especially in times of rapid change you
need feedback so delegations do not
generate even 1/10 of the feedback than
an invitation generates so for example
you invited me onto the shelf right
alright and what happened next I got to
choose the timing of my response the
medium of my response the content of my
response and so many other things around
you know my responding to your send of
that invitation and that's all rich
feedback for you to act on about just
how good or not good this interview
might go right so with delegations you
don't get any of that feedback and in
good agile and good scrum good empirical
process runs on feedback without
feedback you have nothing so the idea
here is yeah continue to delegate but
make some invitations in with your
delegations because here's why because
every invitation has inside of it an
invitation to decide yes or no and it's
it turns out that decisions generate
mindshare and the siding is highly
engaging you know so when you invited me
here's what goes through our mind what
happens if I say no what happens if I
say yes what will I miss if I say no
what will I experience if I say yes all
those things are in my head so when you
invite me you get in my head this is a
very very strong way to lead today
especially when you want to be able to
respond to change responding to change
is about feedback so
invitations generate that feedback they
they engage here your best workers the
ones with options the ones who will
loiter at the exits with their resume if
they smell that smell could you give a
nice tangible example of where
a manager might want to choose to use an
invitation rather than a delegation yeah
let's take an example where let's take
that product owner example you know you
asked me earlier you know how do you
select a good product owner but my
approach would be to find the role
identify people who could fit in the
role and then if there's three or four
opportunities to play the product on a
roll and invite 12 people and let them
know you know the first four who respond
to this they have the job and see what
happens now you're going to get super
enthusiastic all the way in 100% in
product owners instead of foot-dragging
pissy half-hearted product owners well
we should increase the chances of it I
don't think any of these things are
panacea is no but I can see that's that
would be interesting your concept here
dig into it is that putting a decision
into the head of the person who may or
may not do the work is it actually an
important way to generate information
right in this case it is you can figure
out who is interested in this role and
who's not rather than saying sue you
look like the right person to be the
product owner she may not want to be a
product owner but she might feel
compelled to say yes yeah and I could
give you another tangible example of
something that I did in the 90s and the
90s they had a technical services firm
and it grew at about 55 people and I had
operations in three states
I created a benefit which was a books
tippin's right people could spend 500
bucks a year on books and here was a
rule the rule was the book has to
pertain to your job quote in some way
and then it was user to lose it and then
it reset every year in January those
were the rules and the constraints and
everyone was invited to just take
advantage of it
well don't you know how much feedback I
got out of that Jim right so a lot of
people who are working like in.net they
were buying java books I had no idea
they were interested in Java stuff so I
got to talk with them and I found out
that they were real passionate about
Java and I was able to move some things
around and really really keep people
engaged and motivated I got a lot of
data from what books they bought when
they bought them whether they used up
all the stip and what
what you know what they were reading
what they were interested in and and
that's another example of generating
feedback often it off of an invitation
that's it that's a good one what else
can we talk about here what you talked
about the core principles of inviting
leadership could you go into those yeah
there's four things in common with any
good game and any good invitation right
so Jane McGonigal when a book called
reality is broken about I don't know ten
years ago and on page 22 of that book
she defines the properties of a good
game in this four of them and I really
love her definition she says a good game
has a very clear goal second thing it
has is very clear rules or constraints
third thing it has is a way to clearly
track your progress to know what level
you're at and to get feedback and the
fourth property and the most important
one is opt-in participation so it turns
out that these four properties also
apply to any good invitation any good
invitation has has these four properties
clearly defined so in the book what I
described is that there's some real
rigor and discipline that has to be
applied to your invitations in fact you
can't just casually invite someone you
have to really think about it and
structure it properly
unlike delegations which you can just
throw at people you know so it sounds
clinical but it's it's actually very
simple right like you know I can invite
you to dinner now and I could I could
satisfy all four of these properties you
want me to take a shot at that I'll
actually want to use the example of
inviting some people who might be
candidates to be product owners because
that's a little bit more business yeah
yeah so here's how it would go let's say
that I was reciting you know an email
that I can post and I was reading it now
and I'm gonna put it out too so all the
candidates that we believe would be good
product owners maybe it's 20 people all
right that's perfect
wait on preamble you know discuss the
the need the opportunity and the
challenges we face and why we're moving
to scrub and then would say you've been
sure you've been selected as a candidate
to occupy this role you know
it won't be assigned to you you'll have
to choose it you know and here's here's
the goal our intent is to create a
predictable and reliable delivery
function in this company so we have a
delivery machine okay and the product
owners play a critical role they're
actually the hero of the they're the
star of the show
they are the deciders and they have a
lot of authority they also have a lot of
pressure because they have to face the
pressures of the technology teams the
business teams and and they have to
resolve you know they basically lay it
out as an enticing high high profile
role so you know the goal is to improve
our predictability reliability and
quality of our products and you play a
critical role in the vision of our
products what are the rules you'll need
to show up if you're interested in this
at a meeting that's two weeks from today
on Thursday we're will will provide
further information about what this role
is and the gravity of it you must do the
following things before you arrive there
you know thing one thing two thing three
and one of those might be read the scrum
guide right we'll track our progress
through time and tasks through the
meeting and also by who who signs up you
know we need for product owners not
three not five but four and we hope that
you'll consider being one of them the
first four who volunteer so be a vetting
you know be like one more one more sort
of checked before it's final but if you
sign up you know there's a high
likelihood you're gonna get this job and
here's how here's how you'll be measured
you know here's how you track your
progress here's how you'll be your low
where you're at and you're invited now
as we get into the book a little further
you start off by talking about Authority
yeah give me your view of Authority I
have my own views I'd love to hear you
have you articulate from the book or
since then the books a little old and
then we can talk a little bit about
Authority and how one should think about
it yeah so authorities a triggering term
when we go into an organization you know
and we're being introduced around after
you meet the person or when you meet the
person the you know the introducer will
always say oh you know Mary runs
products or marrying ports the so-and-so
and quality you know so you know like
where they are and what their authority
less in the book we define authority as
the right to do a specific kind of work
and some of the most important work you
could possibly do is making decisions
that affect the group as a whole if
you're authorized to do that we call you
a leader if you you know participate in
decisions that affect the group but the
definition of authority in the book is
the right to do a specific kind of work
and then we go on to define power as the
exercise of authority so Authority is a
really deep topic and I'm pulling this
from the group relations community
there's a worldwide community that
studies and implements the work of a
fellow named Alfred beyond the IO n and
they run these conferences in our
empirical where we study authority in
the here and now and they create a
temporary institution in these
conferences where we explore and play
with Authority in a safe kind of a space
away from work and I've attended several
of these and the people that I've met
there have been you know pretty amazing
like like people who run West Point
captains of industry university
professors all kinds of really high
achieving high impact people who are
struggling with the exercise of
authority in their jobs and I'm bringing
that experience and that learning into
the book right so you could think of
authority as the essential information
that describes the group so if I want to
know the group all I need to know is who
has decision rights that's gonna form
the structure so in the book what we say
is if you want to change culture all you
need to do is change who's authorized to
make a decision that will change culture
right away let me hop in here this was
something we believed in a lot at the
Thompson corporation I remember once at
the we used to have these annual top
management meetings like 150 people
something like that and remember as part
of my keynote address I said here is one
of our unfair advantages
against our competition in the Thompson
corporation which like about an eight
billion dollar company 50,000 employees
we have 500 people who are authorized to
waste fifty thousand dollars beautiful I
looked over at the CFO and watched him
cringe but then also smile because he
knew it was true our number one
competitor
mcgraw-hill we know there are three
people who are allowed to waste fifty
thousand dollars and I assert that this
is one of our great competitive
advantage they are mantra at Thompson
was we delegate authority down to the
level were comfortable with and then one
level below that nice I should say this
was Thompson in its heyday in the 90s
they brought in the usual corporate
clowns in the next generation of
management and it ain't that no more but
man did we do some amazing things with
that design of pushing authority down
and of course if you push Authority down
you have to put accountability down so
in both in Thompson it was well-known
you missed your numbers two years in a
row and your head will definitely get
lopped off oh well all right you had all
the authority right and if you it
up it's on you exactly you had danger
and you had opportunity all in one spot
right yeah we had 25 year old guys or I
do or a four years out of college who
you know we're running a five million
dollar business unit they had amazing
Authority and accountability right so
authority authority to do what its
authority to decide in this case
authority to hire and fire design their
budget to once they have their budget
within the you know very broad
flexibility to spend their budget how
they want yeah so authority to decide
when its authority to the edge here's
what happens your company becomes more
responsive to the ever-changing range of
opportunities that are present each day
you know as things change if you if you
centralize control centralized
decision-making authority then you get
to be less responsive that's the bottom
line I will say that this is goes into
evolutionary theory that in a business
space or any kind of competitive space
there are Fitness landscapes that are
either changing rapidly or slowly
and if they're changing very slowly like
say you're a nail factory right hidden
factory a steak Adam Smith's canonical
example yeah probably
you don't need to decentralise to too
much but you really need to optimize or
what they call an evolution exploit you
need to exploit the space make better
pins for less money on the other hand if
you're in the publishing business in
1992 which is when I showed up at
Thompson well at least a few of us knew
damn well that AC a revolutionary sea
change was about to happen in 1992
Thompson got 90% of its revenue from
paper maybe throw in some cd-rom and
what we knew by the by 10 years it would
be the other way around
and so this was gonna be a very rapid
changing environment and he who was most
he or she who was most adaptive on this
fast evolving co-evolutionary landscape
is going to be the winners we basically
went from number four to number one in
ten years by being wasteful it's
interesting our profit margin was always
a little lower than mcgraw-hill a couple
points mm-hmm but our ability to
transition from the old world order to
the new world order was vastly more
rapid and that was the do-or-die thing
at that time isn't that interesting that
you're mentioning that this idea of you
know sending distributing authority to
the edge and that there's some what we
might call necessary waste involved
there there's a felony in John Age
Harland you probably know him because he
was a trustee in a external professor at
Santa Fe do you know him great friend of
mine and one of my most important
mentors in my scientific third career
well isn't that interesting I just I've
just come across the most remarkable
book by this man I've never seen a book
like it it's the title of signals and
boundaries building blocks for complex
adaptive systems Jim I have not read
that one but I am going to this is a
super interesting book because those
signals at the edge right when you and
power decision make you know the
individuals at the edge with
decision-making authority they're at the
edge where the where the signal is and
and they can actually respond because
they have the ability to decide so this
man John
and he writes extensively in his book he
uses like microbiological cellular
theory to describe what goes on in
social systems and and that's exactly
what we wrote about in the inviting
leadership book as well so you know it's
extremely interesting about this
boundary management stuff and in
particular concerning decision rights
the boundaries unauthorized decision
rights and that's your next point in the
book so let's talk about that yeah so
that it turns out that like most of the
impediments to good throughput in most
organizations is because they haven't
refactored the what I call the authority
distribution schema or the distribution
of decision rights to the world changes
we have a reorg but the reorg comes too
late you know it's this is latency so
you know with scrum what we're doing is
we're you're creating a lot of
responsiveness around this by creating
the conditions where the authorized
decision rights are in the right place
so that impediments to good product high
quality product reliable predictable
product delivery are removed the biggest
impediment to delivery is the way we're
making decisions that's what's actually
going on around the world so we we make
decisions a certain way the world
changes we keep making decisions that
way now there's an impediment to
throughput right so this whole idea of
authorized decision rights and
continuously refactoring that so that
the impediments to good product and all
the things we say we want the goals were
trying to see those that those
impediments are minimized or even
completely removed because my hypothesis
and the thing that I coach executives on
is that the way decisions are being made
in the organization is actually the
place where all the problems are
absolutely and in fact I go a little
further which I'll say what is an
organization but a signal processing
system whose output is decisions exactly
that isn't that so true so
so the book inviting leadership
basically offers the assertion in the
hypothesis that if you distribute
decision rights which is what you're
actually doing with imitation that you
become a more responsive organization in
a time of you know high magnitude change
technology these I was listening to the
Apple financial results for the quarter
there's 1.3 billion Apple devices out
there now this is totally transforming
society I was saying to my wife Roberta
that it's not changing the fabric of
society the technology is the fabric so
what's happening here is the pace of
change is speeding up it's hitting
businesses first they're stuck in the
mud in the way that they're making
decisions and they can't get out of
their own way and these companies are
going to get acquired they're gonna be
run over by by fast-moving nimble
competitors smaller ones startups with
nothing to lose and this is this is what
we're up against so in inviting
leadership what we're doing is we're
actually taking an empirical approach to
leadership that's what the books all
about let me add one light final tuning
and then we're gonna have to wrap up
here we're about at our time which is I
would extend the authority with a little
cloud around it of signaling and I'm
gonna give you a real live example one
of my collection of businesses I was in
charge of and I was at Thompson I was a
group CEO or whatever the hell that is
and one of my businesses was one that
would periodically have serious problems
on short timeframe and we had pushed a
lot of authority down to the head of
that business unit as would be usual but
because of the nature of the business
there could be things that were beyond a
reasonable amount of scope to push down
to a 27 year old guy and so I told him
Chris should there ever be and hire and
I was a busy son-of-a-bitch in those
days I made up my time was scheduled in
15 minute blocks and it was just nuts
but anyway I always told him Chris
there's this decision that is above your
large but not infinite delegation of
authority and you need me to make it
right now come and stand on my desk
beautiful and even if I'm in the middle
of a meeting he was a very athletic guy
like a former wrestler I think anyway
one time
he actually did that and sure his
it was a mission-critical
decision that had to be made like in the
next three hours or there would be large
consequences and so he appropriately
used singling to extend his own
authority no isn't that interesting that
you you defined a protocol exactly
literally it's a protocol it's a
protocol that's what you actually did
and and that's a structured interaction
that's a very very high-functioning kind
of behavior so that signals symbols and
signage right there's a whole science
around this called semiotic Jim right
yeah purse right famous Percy and the
theories of semiotics exactly so so a
subset of this is is biosemiotics that
is you know this is a signaling ensign
engines in symbolic aspects of
biological systems right in the inviting
leadership book we introduced a further
subset of semiotic which we call
leadership semiotic sand that's actually
the story that you just told was the
story about leadership semiotic so so
leaders can think of themselves as
signaling devices in the in the social
system right so when we go down the
highway driving we use signage and
symbols and signals to keep ourselves
safe right we use the signs along the
road to find their way and then we
signal you know to the other vehicles
that are moving you know what our
intentions are so we signal our intent
through directional signaling this is
what leaders are doing right so so
people are listening very carefully to
what they say and what they do and
leadership semiotic s-- is actually a
very big deal cool I didn't be knowing I
was no semiotic
I love purse
Charles purse probably America's
greatest philosopher but he doesn't
write like a philosopher you can
actually read this stuff and there's a
wonderful collection of his writings on
semiotic skald purse on signs you can
get it on Amazon for 20 bucks something
like that well we're about at our clock
here Daniel this has been wonderful I
think this has been just the kind of
conversation I was hoping to have and
there's still like seven more topic
points we didn't get to but that's all
right keep the audience
wanting more right that's all idea okay
Jim thanks a lot for having me on the
show I'm very honored to be on the show
and to be included in such a list of
people I mean the list of interviewees
you have is just amazing and you know
listen to several of the episodes and
they've been they've been edifying and
enriched and you know nourishing you
know they have a high nutritional
content this episode I hope will do the
same production services and audio
editing by jerod Jane's consulting music
by Tom Muller at modern space music dot